{"tossups": [{"question": "Archibald Wavell led relief e\u21b5orts during this event, which was covered up until Ian Stephens of<em> The</em> <em>Statesman</em> published graphic photographs of this event\u2019s victims. During this event, a \u201cboat denial\u201d policy destroyed boats in ports susceptible to invasion by the Japanese, whose occupation of Burma worsened this event. Winston Churchill blamed this event\u2019s victims for \u201cbreeding like rabbits\u201d and questioned why Gandhi did not die in it. British hoarding of rice is often blamed for, for the point, what 1943 event that killed over 2 million people in a province of British India?", "answer": "<b> Bengal Famine</b> of 1943 (accept descriptive answers that mention both underlined ideas and/or their equivalents; prompt on partial answers, like \u201c(Indian) famine\u201d)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This battle is the subject of the last of Lactantius\u2019 \u201cDeaths of the Persecutors.\u201d The loser of this battle erroneously thought that a prophecy in the Sibylline Books favored him. After the Praetorian Guard supported this battle\u2019s losing commander, the winner disbanded it. The words \u201cIn hoc signo vinces,\u201d or\u201cIn this sign you shall conquer,\u201d appeared to the winner of this battle, who had the losing commander, Maxentius, beheaded. A dream of a cross preceded, for the point, what decisive 312 AD battle on the Tiber River that was won by Constantine the Great?", "answer": "Battle of<b> Milvian Bridge</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "Description acceptable. This speech urged its listeners to dedicate themselves \u201cto tame the savageness of man and make gentle the life of this world\u201d after asking for a prayer. This speech quotes Aeschylus [ess-kuh-luss] to describe how pain can be turned into \u201cwisdom through the awful grace of God.\u201d This impromptu speech, which urges against the polarization of racial hatred, was delivered in just under five minutes from the back of a truck in Indianapolis and is credited with preventing a riot. For the point, name this 1968 speech delivered by a Democratic presidential hopeful in response to an assassination that had taken place that night in Memphis.", "answer": "<b> R</b>obert F.<b> Kennedy</b>\u2019s speech on the<b> assassination</b> of Martin Luther<b> King</b> Jr. (accept<b> RFK </b>or<b> MLK</b> in place of their names; prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This author of the Nanjung diary was imprisoned after failing to capture enemy forces and replaced by Won Gyun. This man, who forbade the announcement of his death at the Battle of Noryang, had been reinstated by King Seonjo before the Battle of Myeongnyang, where he preserved all 12 of his<em> panokseon</em>. This man\u2019s alliance with Ming China led to the end of the Imjin War and the Japanese retreat from Busan. For the point, name this admiral of the Joseon dynasty who used turtle ships to defend Korea.", "answer": "<b> Yi</b> Sun-sin", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A publication commissioned for Charles V illustrates previous rulers based in this city, the amount of tribute they paid, and di\u21b5erent types of professions including lapidaries and featherworkers. This city, which was divided in four by canals, featured a \u201csacred precinct\u201d with a double pyramid called the Templo Mayor. The frontispiece of the Codex Mendoza illustrates the founding of this capital city where an eagle landed on a cactus. For the point, name this city, the center of the Aztec Empire and basis of modern-day Mexico City.", "answer": "<b> Tenochtitlan</b> (do not accept or prompt on Mexico City)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "An organization dedicated to fighting this ideology controversially employed Roy Bullock to conduct illegal surveillance operations and was led for many years until 2015 by Abraham Foxman. This ideology was the motivating factor in a trial that convicted a man for Mary Phagan\u2019s murder. The lynching of Leo Frank was motivated by this ideology, which Henry Ford promoted through his newspaper<em> The Dearborn</em> <em>Independent</em>. The Anti-Defamation League was founded to oppose, for the point, what type of religious prejudice whose common name was coined in late 19th-century Germany?", "answer": "<b> anti-Semitism</b> (accept equivalent descriptions of<b> anti-Jewish</b> sentiment)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "The author of<em> Black Hawk Down</em>, Mark Bowden, wrote the definitive biography of this man in 2001. This owner of the Naples Estate was specifically targeted for capture or elimination by the first Search Bloc. This man agreed to a period of nominal captivity at La Catedral prison in exchange for a deal preventing his extradition to the U.S. For the point, name this leader of the Medellin Cartel who was the leading smuggler of cocaine prior to his 1993 death in Colombia.", "answer": "Pablo<b> Escobar</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This treaty was preceded by a document signed at Passau after the military victories of Maurice of Saxony, and by an interim ruling declared after a king defeated the Schmalkaldic League. This agreement contained a clause protecting knights, the<em> Declaratio Ferdinandei</em>, and its failure to include Calvinism arguably worsened tensions that led to the Thirty Years\u2019 War. This treaty established the principle of\u201cwhose realm, whose religion\u201d for Catholicism and Lutheranism. For the point, name this 1555 treaty signed in a namesake city of the Holy Roman Empire.", "answer": "Peace of<b> Augsburg</b> (accept<b> Augsburg</b> Settlement)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "People in this industry included Benjamin Lundy and his colleague, who created \u201cThe Black List.\u201dAnother man of this industry hid his equipment in Winthrop Gilman\u2019s warehouse; Thomas Dimmock found the grave of that member of this industry who, five days before his death, had given a speech in Alton. A member of this industry declared \u201cI will not retreat a single inch - and I will be heard\u201d in performing this job for<em> The Liberator</em>. Elijah Lovejoy, William Lloyd Garrison, and other abolitionists worked in, for the point, what industry that allowed them to publish anti-slavery news articles?", "answer": "<b> journalism</b> (accept equivalents relating to<b> newspaper</b>s or to the<b> editing</b> profession; prompt on publishing before mentioned; prompt on abolitionism before mentioned by asking the player \u201cyes, they\u2019re abolitionists, but in what industry did they work?\u201d)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This body of water was once named after John Bigler, with its name later changed because of Bigler\u2019s secessionist sympathies. The 1960 Winter Olympics were held west of this lake in a previously undeveloped resort named for a slur against Native American women. John C. Fremont was the first person of European descent to encounter this lake, whose surrounding area provided timber for settlers attracted to the Comstock Lode. This lake is east of Truckee and another lake named for the Donner Party. For the point, name this sixth-largest lake in the US, located on the California-Nevada boundary.", "answer": "Lake<b> Tahoe</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "One military commander in this government was a former leader of the January Uprising in Poland named Jaroslav Dabrowski. Female supporters of this government who burned down most of a city were called petroleuses [petro-loozes]. Armies led by Patrice de MacMahon on the orders of Adolphe Thiers [tee-air] put down this government, whose supporters were sent to New Caledonia after it was crushed and Louis Blanqui was imprisoned. For the point, name this government that arose after the Franco-Prussian War and held France\u2019s capital in 1871.", "answer": "<b> Paris Commune</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This character tells his wife \u201can everlasting funeral marches round your heart\u201d in a dialogue where he compares his household to a courtroom. This character is told \u201cI will save you tomorrow...From yourself I will save you\u201d in an oft-deleted Act 2, Scene 2. When asked to recite the Ten Commandments, this character forgets the commandment forbidding adultery. This character tears up his written confession, causing him to be hung for witchcraft. For the point, name this protagonist of Arthur Miller\u2019s<em> The</em> <em>Crucible</em>.", "answer": "<b> John Proctor</b> (accept either or both names)", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Drama"}, {}, {"question": "The Great Wild Goose Pagoda was built in this city to hold valuable scriptures brought by the monk Xuanzang [sh\u2019uan-zang]. Zhang Xueliang [jahng shweh-leeahng] held Chiang Kai-shek hostage in a 1936 incident named after this city, trying to force him to work with the Communist Party to resist Japanese invasion. The Silk Road had its eastern origin in this city, where Emperor Qin Shi Huangdi was buried with his Terracotta Army. For the point, name this city also referred to as Chang\u2019an, an ancient capital of several Chinese dynasties, including the Han and Tang.", "answer": "<b> Xi\u2019an</b> ([shee-ahn]; accept<b> Chang\u2019an</b> before \u201cZhang Xueliang\u201d is read, and prompt on it after)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "ishan [shee-shahn]. These weapons were produced by Auto-Ordnance, which was founded by this weapon\u2019s namesake. Frank and Peter Gusenberg were killed via this weapon. One of these weapons sold for $130,000 at a 2012 auction because it was allegedly used by Bonnie and Clyde. Seven members of the North Side Gang in Chicago were killed by these weapons during the St. Valentine\u2019s Day Massacre. The\u201cChicago Typewriter\u201d is a nickname of, for the point, what \u201cgun that made the twenties roar,\u201d used by Prohibition-era criminals?", "answer": "<b> Thompson</b> submachine gun (accept the<b> Tommy</b> Gun; accept<b> M1921</b>; accept<b> Model 1921</b>; prompt on (sub)machine gun)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A man from this country came up with a namesake device to display declination, meridian, and celestial equator known as Gemma\u2019s rings. Another man from this country is considered the first to posit that the continents drifted apart from a central landmass; that man also created the<em> Theatrus Orbis</em> <em>Terrarum</em>, a work often considered the first atlas. Another man from this country decided to use straight lines to represent east-west and north-south directions, resulting in the erroneous portrayal of Africa as smaller than Greenland. Gerard Mercator was from, for the point, what country where the science of cartography thrived in Amsterdam?", "answer": "Republic of the (Seven) United<b> Netherlands</b> (accept the<b> Dutch</b> Republic)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This city was home to a gang of Latvian immigrants led by Peter the Painter, who gained fame for allegedly surviving the Siege of Sidney Street. A magazine headquartered in this city,<em> Oz</em>, was subject to an obscenity trial for its \u201cSchoolkids Edition\u201d after a crackdown by the Obscene Publications Squad. In 1936, protesters clashed with Oswald Mosley\u2019s fascists in, for the point, what city\u2019s Cable Street, where anti-fascist protesters were harshly treated by this city\u2019s \u201cBobbies\u201d in the East End?", "answer": "<b> London</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man introduced a Petroleum Gas Revenue Tax to subsidize the eastern region of his country as part of his National Energy Policy. Under pressure from China, this man barred Taiwan from his country\u2019s Olympics. After Jimmy Cross was kidnapped by the FLQ, this man used the War Measures Act for the first time in peacetime; during that event, this man declared \u201cJust watch me\u201d in suppressing the October Crisis. For the point, name this Canadian Prime Minister and father of Justin, the current PM.", "answer": "<b> P</b>ierre Elliot<b> Trudeau</b> (prompt on Trudeau)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "In 1891, police chief David Hennessy blamed members of this ethnicity for his murder by uttering a slur on his deathbed, leading to the lynching of eleven people of this ethnicity in New Orleans. An\u201cAppeal to the American People\u201d was written by Anatole France after members of this ethnicity were sentenced to death by Webster Thayer, who was prejudiced against them in their trials for murder and robbing the Slater and Morrill Shoe company in Braintree, Massachusetts in 1920. For the point, name this ethnicity of the anarchists Sacco and Vanzetti.", "answer": "<b> Italian</b> Americans", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This group included the lyrics \u201cI don\u2019t want to be a soldier / Who the captain of some sinking ship / Would stow, far below\u201d in the anti-war song \u201cViolet Hill.\u201d One of this group\u2019s experimental albums describes a world called Silentia, where the government attempts to steal sound and color; that album includes songs like \u201cEvery Teardrop is a Waterfall.\u201d<em> Mylo Xyloto</em> was produced by this band, which performed \u201cFix You\u201d and played Oasis\u2019 \u201cDon\u2019t Look Back in Anger\u201d with Ariana Grande at the One Love Manchester concert. \u201cYellow\u201d and \u201cViva la Vida\u201d are hits by, for the point, what British band fronted by Chris Martin?", "answer": "<b> Coldplay</b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "In wartime, these people made use of<em> pa</em>, or fortified hill fortresses that could be quickly abandoned. George Grey served as the governor over these peoples\u2019 territory, which was forcibly confiscated in the 1863 Settlements Act. Hone Heke [ho-neh HEH-keh] was a leader of these people, who cut down British colors flying on top of a hill, leading to the outbreak of the Flagsta\u21b5War. After the importation of European weaponry, tribal leaders from this group of people fought each other in the Musket Wars. For the point, name this indigenous people of New Zealand.", "answer": "<b> Maori</b> people (prompt on indigenous people of New Zealand before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This man\u2019s book<em> The True Law of Free Monarchies</em> defended the divine right of kings, and he tried to marry his son in the Spanish Match. Puritans met with this king in the Hampton Court Conference. Sir Walter Raleigh plotted against this man in the Main Plot, which was paired with the Bye Plot. Guy Fawkes led a conspiracy to blow up Parliament with gunpowder during the reign of, for the point, what English king who united the thrones of Scotland and England and names a famous translation of the Bible?", "answer": "<b> James I</b> of England (or<b> James VI of Scotland</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "Thomas Dart rearranged two of this composer\u2019s recorder sonatas as the<em> Fitzwilliam Sonatas</em>. This composer\u2019s anthem<em> Sing Unto God</em> was written for the wedding of Frederick, Prince of Wales. A Sinfonia for two oboes and strings is known as \u201cThe Arrival of the Queen of Sheba\u201d and is from his oratorio <em>Solomon</em>. This frequent collaborator with Charles Jennens included bourees and hornpipes in a set of three suites commissioned by King George I for a barge concert on the Thames River. For the point, name this Baroque composer of<em> Water Music</em> and<em> Messiah</em>.", "answer": "George Friedrich<b> Handel</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "Two of this military campaign\u2019s leaders were later defeated by the Bulgarian Tsar Kaloyan. Support for this campaign was raised by Fulk of Neuilly\u2019s [noo-yee\u2019s] preaching. This conflict, led by Boniface of Montferrat, was marred by looting after Emperor Alexios IV failed to pay its participants. Soldiers fighting in this campaign were forced to sack the city of Zara on the orders of Enrico Dandolo. Baldwin of Flanders was established as the first Latin Emperor after, for the point, what early 13th century crusade in which Constantinople was sacked?", "answer": "<b> Fourth Crusade</b> (\u201dcrusade\u201d not needed after mentioned)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This modern country was the site of the Battle of Ghazni, a major defeat for Hyder Khan. William Elphinstone was captured in this so-called \u201cgraveyard of empires;\u201d the destruction of his army is depicted in the Elizabeth Butler\u2019s painting<em> Remnants of an Army</em>. Alpha group and Zenith group captured Tajbeg palace in this country, leading to the death of President Hafizullah Amin and the installation of the Soviet backed Babrak Karmal. American special forces backed the Northern Alliance in this country after invading it in 2001. For the point, name this country once ruled by the Taliban.", "answer": "<b> Afghanistan</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "In a letter to James Madison, this man proposed a one-year waiting period before bills take e\u21b5ect and a one-term limit for the presidency. In a letter to John Holmes, this man compared the passage of the Missouri Compromise to the horror of a \u201cfire bell in the night,\u201d as he opposed restricting slavery in the territories. In a letter to the Danbury Baptists, this man called for a \u201cwall of separation between Church and State.\u201d For the point, name this man who received many congratulatory letters upon winning the presidency in 1801.", "answer": "Thomas<b> Jefferson</b> <b>Extra Question</b> Only read if moderator botches a question.", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "At this American battle, explorer Henry Morton Stanley fought and was captured. At this battle, Leonidas Polk and Braxton Bragg commanded the left and center of the Confederate lines. Until the Battle of Antietam, this was the bloodiest battle of the Civil War, largely due to heavy concentrated fighting around the \u201cHornet\u2019s Nest.\u201d After this battle, a Confederate fleet near Memphis was destroyed. Until Antietam, this was the bloodiest battle in American history. For the point, name this 1862 victory for the Union in Tennessee.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Shiloh</b> (accept Battle of<b> Pittsburg Landing</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}], "bonuses": []}